Here's a reflection on a familiar phrase we rarely examine closely: the essay "Life is Short" by Paul Graham, written in January 2016.
Graham begins with a childhood question.
Is life actually short, or are we just complaining about the fact that it ends?
For years he had no way to answer this.
Then he had children, and the answer became clear: life really is short.
What changed his mind was learning to convert time, a continuous quantity, into discrete units.
You only get fifty-two weekends with your two-year-old.
If the magic of Christmas lasts from ages three to ten, you'll watch your child experience it just eight times.
And eight, he notes, is not a lot of anything.
Like a handful of eight peanuts, the quantity feels plainly limited.
So life is short. Does knowing this matter? For Graham, it does.
It gives real force to the phrase "life is too short for that." If you find yourself
thinking it, you should try to eliminate whatever it is.
What is life too short for?
The word that comes to his mind is bullshit, the junk food of experience.
He means unnecessary meetings, pointless disputes, bureaucracy, posturing, cleaning up
other people's mistakes, traffic jams, and addictive but unrewarding pastimes.
This junk enters your life in two ways.
Some is forced on you by circumstance, since making money is mostly errands.
But you can reduce even that by prioritizing bullshit-avoidance over money and prestige,
choosing better employers, or, as a freelancer, dropping toxic customers.
The other kind sneaks in by tricking you, and that's harder to remove, because it has to be good at deceiving you.
His example is arguing online.
When someone attacks you, your instinct is to defend yourself, but it's usually better not to.
Otherwise, he says, those people are literally taking your life.
And as technology advances, the things we enjoy grow more addictive, so we must consciously ask: is this how I want to spend my time?
Beyond avoiding waste, we should actively seek what matters.
Most people only gradually learn to tell the difference.
For the young, much confusion comes from artificial situations, worrying what other kids think, which nearly every adult later regrets.
One useful test: ask whether you'll still care about something in the future.
Fake importance has a sharp peak that jabs at you but little substance beneath.
Meanwhile, having coffee with a friend genuinely matters. Small children matter too.
When they tug your sleeve and ask you to play, that's usually the bullshit-minimizing choice.
Because life is short, its shortness surprises us.
We take things for granted, then they're gone. The saddest windows close when people die.
After his mother's death, Graham wished he'd spent more time with her.
His answer isn't to dwell morbidly on death, but to cultivate impatience about the things you most want to do.
Don't wait to climb the mountain, write the book, or visit your mother. Just don't wait.
When you don't have much of something, you can try to get more and savor what you have.
How you live affects how long you live, but paying closer attention to your time matters even more.
It is possible to slow time.
Children help, filling life with moments too perfect to ignore.
His closing advice is simple and clear: relentlessly prune bullshit, don't wait to do the
things that matter, and savor the time you have.
That's what you do when life is short.